[SPEAKER_01]: This is a verse I would like to read out from the Theragāṭṭha, verse 6.13 by Sīrimandhā.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the section...
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't read the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The world is beaten down by death and surrounded by old age.
[SPEAKER_01]: A dance of craving has laid it low and it's always fuming with desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: The world is beaten down by death
[SPEAKER_01]: encircled, surrounded by old age, beaten constantly, without respite, like a thief being flogged.
[SPEAKER_01]: Three things are coming, like a wall of flame.
[SPEAKER_01]: Death, disease, and old age.
[SPEAKER_01]: No power can stand before them, and no speed enough to flee.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't waste your day, a little or a lot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every night that passes,
[SPEAKER_01]: It shortens your life by that much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Walking or standing, sitting or lying down, your final night draws near.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no time to be careless.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, walking or standing, sitting or laying down, you should be dwelling on the
[SPEAKER_00]: Ultimate context, which is what death is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an ultimate context to your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a non-negotiable context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people might think, oh, I must be going through the motions and methods of practicing mindfulness of death, thinking about it when I'm walking, when I'm sitting.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's true only in a sense that you need to discern the most fundamental
[SPEAKER_00]: Always present possibility of death, which is why it makes it such an ultimate context of your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything else within your life can come and go, that has been, could have not been, all these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But one thing for sure, when life is there, death is its guarantee, as the final outcome of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the reason why people would be
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason why people are oppressed and oppressed by their desires, by their intentions, unskillful actions, is because you turn a blind eye to this very factual liability to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, death... possibility of death is certain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Death is possible in a way of... what is possible is you might die this way or that way, but possibility of death is certain.
[SPEAKER_00]: As an outcome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if a person would not be turning a blind eye to it, that's already something that's gonna start shaping your life differently.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because many... pretty much everything unwholesome that a person can engage with, that you can engage with, is on account of ignoring the fact that you will die, ignoring the fact that you will not always be healthy, not always be young, being intoxicated by those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you entertain desire, you want more of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all you need to do is uncover that fundamental context of, well, certainty of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it will already prevent you, automatically prevent you from how far you would be able to proliferate down the rabbit hole of desires and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what mindfulness of death means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you can do that on a very loose level.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can start narrowing it down and you realize that you might not see the end of this day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not necessarily you must have to like become neurotic about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will die, I will die.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just, no, recognize that possibility is so immediate that you might not see the end of the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might not see the end of the morning.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might not have enough time to finish your meal.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might not have enough time to breathe out once you breathe in.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how much you're not in control of your life fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't mean that you should be trying to... like you should be repeating to yourself that you will die every second of your day.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not contemplation of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just mechanical repetition of the idea of what death is for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to understand the context of death, which is that
[SPEAKER_00]: Ultimate peripheral context to everything you actually do in your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, hence the mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever there is a principle of peripheral, there is a principle of mindfulness, peripheral awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by being mindful of of the context of death in regard to your day-to-day life, that's already mindfulness, practice of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if a person wants to start practicing, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: That contemplation of death as meditation, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: As with any other meditation, withdraw yourself from distractions, from company, and yeah, think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think, like, if you don't know where to start, just think about the nature of death that is inescapable to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, it's gonna come, and you can, which then, you take that further and start thinking, okay, so, what is
[SPEAKER_00]: What would be the real significance then, of this life, that is fully within that control of death?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because whatever you do in this life, cannot make you step outside of the liability to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot basically free you from death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then you start, when you realize that that order cannot change,
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what you distract yourself with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what you accomplish with this life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fundamentally, that whole thing, as much as you developed it, as far as it proliferated, it's still equally within the domain of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't escape that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the practice then would be, eh... establishing that right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't matter what you do in this life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fundamentally, you're liable to sickness, aging and death.
[SPEAKER_00]: The context is not something you need to keep in front of you and think about.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll die.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will die.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just keep it at the back of your mind, where it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, while I'm doing this, this and this, I might die.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's highly likely I'll die as a result of, you know, sitting in my room reading a book.
[SPEAKER_00]: But death is equally present there, because my life depends upon working organs, upon beating heart, breathing lungs.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to practice mindfulness of death, you see that your life is undermined by the random operation of organs that you have no control over.
[SPEAKER_01]: What about the example of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I gave earlier with the... You're on call.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have a job.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be called to work at any point.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be called, because you've chosen that job.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever you do,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean by context, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not a context you can be indifferent to, because it's a context that undermines and affects your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, oh, yeah, the simile of that would be, for example, let's say you have, what would it be?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, like a job interview.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have one shot at something that can change your life in a week's time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever you do for that week, this will be at the back of your mind, because it is so important.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will be...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a degree of concern in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, imagine if that one shot, it's basically death.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like a random interview that can go either way.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's as fundamental as losing your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize what kind of concern would that be, peripherally, and how much influence would that have on your choices and decisions in this life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the dhammapada verse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it was about anger, wasn't it, in the very beginning, where it said... how do you go?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's those... yeah, those who quarrel, they forget that we are all gonna die, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That we are all sentenced to death in this life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, quarrels persist and quarrels develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you don't forget the ultimate appointment with death that you have,
[SPEAKER_00]: That can... and also, again, you can't have... like, you know, you can have a job appointment exactly... exact time, exact day, but appointment with death is uncertain in the sense that it can arise at any given time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize that appointment might be today, might be tomorrow, might be in ten years' time.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't forget about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I cannot forget about it because it can be here the next moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I forget about it, I might fail.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever you do then in this life, you do it on the basis of not forgetting about the ultimate context of your liability to die.
[SPEAKER_00]: Certain possibility of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that already you could see how much less you would be able to be pulled by the fleeting desires of the senses or distractions and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just... you just would not make... it would not have any value.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, again, if you ever... if a person has any doubt about it, just recollect when you feared for your life, for a period of time, on account of anything, illness or accident or whatever, and see how much interest you had in the world during that period of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, very little.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were not enjoying your food.
[SPEAKER_00]: You were not finding solace in friends and distraction and parties or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just... this was the most pressing thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's basically...
[SPEAKER_00]: Reconnecting to that context that is there, so you don't have to fabricate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have to stop covering it up with that constant, like, influx of sensuality and the intentions for distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you always feel like you're on call, that you might be called upon by death, that's already means you already develop fundamentally that proper context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which now shapes your decisions, makes you non-careless in regard to things in front of you in your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's essentially what mindfulness of death is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness of the certain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, today I have to do this, I have to work in the garden, and I have to go this, I have to go supermarket, or... and you... All these things can stay, but you would see how much less emotionally you would be pulled or affected by
[SPEAKER_00]: Any of those things, whether they change, whether they're the way you wanted them to be or they go the other way, you wouldn't be affected.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you were not there with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're concerned about death.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that kind of practice can be a bit too sharp for some people.
[SPEAKER_00]: That concern can overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if it doesn't, you could see how quickly you would develop this passion in regard to everything that comes your way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the Buddha praised it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's pretty much the quickest way to free your mind from any unwholesome state and ignorance and avoidance of responsibility and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if it's too much, then you practice mindfulness of breathing, because it results in the same, as we spoke in the other talks.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize that your fully controlled act of breathing depends on things that are not your own, while you're controlling it, which means your own sense of control is undermined by fundamentally depending upon things you cannot control.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that verse you mentioned, you know, dhammapada, it's also in the Therakārtha, others don't understand that our lives must have limits, or our lives have limits.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those who do understand this, settle their quarrels right away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're saying it's the most important thing to your life, is the fact that you have an appointment
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you... like, you can also use that in the reverse order and you can see.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you think, oh, but I am practicing mindfulness of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am making the effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is my mind getting angry?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is my mind getting lustful?
[SPEAKER_00]: If the answer is yes, it means you have an established context of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you were, you would not... these things would not be able to arise, let alone persist.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be doing trivial things or getting wound up, triggered by trivial matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only time, the only way you can be triggered by trivial matters, or non-trivial matters, the only way you could be emotionally triggered by anything, is if you have lost the context of certain death.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's you and yours only.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, literally, nothing else matters, because everything is within that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing you can do, say or think, that will not be within the context of life that's undermined by death.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just cannot...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the practice of mindfulness of death, as I said, it's not a mechanical repetition of certain thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will die or trying to keep it in front of you and not forget about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's really just clarifying the understanding of that inherent context in whatever you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: The context of that ultimate final cessation that that you cannot even conceive escaping from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you think about escaping from, the thoughts of that escape are within.
[SPEAKER_00]: The context of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're fully enclosed by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it can be quite frightening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like being buried alive, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're still alive, but you realize the escape from this is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the simile that Buddha gave to that king.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he said, what if I tell you there is a big mountain coming to crush you from... An army.
[SPEAKER_00]: An army coming from the east.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll go west.
[SPEAKER_00]: What if it's coming from the west?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll go north.
[SPEAKER_00]: What if it's coming from west, north and east?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll go south.
[SPEAKER_01]: What if it's coming from all four directions?
[SPEAKER_00]: Mountains enclosing you and you can't escape, you can't fight against it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What would you do then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, well, then I will re-evaluate my life and maybe become a monk and try and free myself internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, that's what life is.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no escape in any direction from that liability to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's on the basis of simply ignoring that obvious truth, not letting it sink in,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people get up to all sorts of unwholesome, horrible things as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: People can do just on account of not...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like the duty, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you do that, you don't have to worry about most of the other things that you worry about.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what you've got to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you replace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is better?
[SPEAKER_00]: Thousands of worries that overwhelm you every single day or just develop one fundamental concern, whereby everything else is included and nothing can affect you on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a good deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, not for the mind that's not trained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not for the mind that hasn't developed virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't see that as a good deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just see that as a direct threat and terror.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they still have a view that sensuality, distraction, acts of will-will, anything, any little things that you do based on passion, they still value that as a mean of escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: They imply that if I don't think about death, I'm not affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not like a rational thought that they pre-planned.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simply, the habit of ignoring maintains that ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you feel like you're sheltered from death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until, of course, circumstances remind you that it's otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until you have little pangs of anxiety that then you can't get rid of for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you never admit to yourself what's obvious right from the start.
[SPEAKER_00]: That as soon as you're born, you're old enough to die, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: The second you come... you're conceived,
[SPEAKER_00]: You're liable to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's really not even a negotiable context.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people might say, oh, you shouldn't be thinking about this because you won't enjoy life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you won't enjoy life in an unwholesome sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you certainly appreciate it in a wholesome sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a possibility of developing wisdom, they will then free you from death.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a possibility for doing good and maybe showing others who want to hear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is still plenty you can do in this life within the context of death that won't be as futile as simply distracting yourself from the obvious truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to, as you're saying, open up to the fact of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to open up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't close yourself off to that idea, to that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you close yourself, it will be out of fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, okay, you might not be able to take it all in at once, which is fine, but you should certainly not develop a view that you shouldn't be taking it at all, because it's making you scared.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to be developing then yourself in regard to that which scares you, so whereby you won't run away from that which frightens you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you get to understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha says that monks should think, um, I could die today, a snake could bite me, I could fall down, the elements might change and destroy me, my body might get sick, my heart, centipedes, whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Accidents.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if he thinks, oh, this could happen, that could happen, this could happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he doesn't go mindlessly through the motions of snake might bite me, I might fall, my heart might stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He thinks these things to re-evoke the context of I am susceptible to dying at any given moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having established that context, he doesn't need to keep thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now, whatever he does already maintains the context, because that already is implying, yeah, it can end at any given moment, because you can die.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's poisonous snakes in the field.
[SPEAKER_01]: It could kill you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't...
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to repeat yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The snakes are in the field.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness, properly done, it's on the level of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know means the thing is there, present.
[SPEAKER_00]: The context is there, present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why mindfulness and memory recollecting, it goes hand in hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not a mechanical focusing technique that you will be doing on account of different meditation objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's really developing the knowledge of the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there are snakes in the field.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't go around, snakes are in the field, snakes are in the field.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever you step in the field, that's the context of the field.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you don't actively think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever a little grass moves and touches you, and you know that from experience, moves and touches your ankle, you are there, instantaneously.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the context is there, because it's fully understood and became part of being in the field, walking in the wilderness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't think about it, because it's there now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's became part of the significance of the thing that you're experiencing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that cannot be done mindlessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes part of the significance when you understood it as part of significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what we mean watchfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you don't forget about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think even Ajahn Chah gave a similar example.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was like a mother that has to go and do the work outside and leave the baby inside.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: She's out there only for the amount of time, minimum amount she has to finish the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: She doesn't linger.
[SPEAKER_00]: She doesn't forget about her baby.
[SPEAKER_00]: She doesn't distract herself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means whatever she's doing, the back of her mind still maintains the importance of a certain context.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when she's done, she goes back to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like the development of mind, the development of mindfulness, the importance of their watchfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: If she doesn't go down the street, leave the kid alone, or get drunk, maybe something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_00]: If she cares, if she has concern about the child, she wouldn't be doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a boundary for her.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why would I then be breaking the precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would I then be careless?
[SPEAKER_00]: When I might die within 10 seconds, my heart might stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it probably won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but it might.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's more than enough for that right concern, right type of concern.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, like, you know, like the Noble Eightfold Path, the right view, right intention and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could say that the entire Noble Eightfold Path is predicated on developing right concern, being concerned rightly, becoming aware of that existential anxiety or dread, whatever you want to call it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you could say it's a right concern that comes through right responsibility, and then the right view will come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha meant as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, I'm teaching suffering and freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: First means you need to know how to start suffering properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right concern, the right displeasure, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The nature of, oh, hold on, this is not a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is not negotiable either.
[SPEAKER_00]: This concerns you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be compared to other concerns, to other people.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just my and my only.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is the only thing worth dealing with.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only thing you can deal with, truly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, developing the right concern, develops the right Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mindfulness of death or the practice of death, again, just sit quietly and think about... well, you could even think about your beating heart or your breathing lungs.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, don't negate nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing to negate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just be aware that, like, I am breathing now, but I might not be able to.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the practice of trying to think about the different ways that you could die.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that only can be indirect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, see, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: People only regard things that they can think about actually directly in front of me, as something that I developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to be discerning the context of what's in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you keep making that context as that in front of you, means the context of that is not in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, there is something peripheral to whatever it's in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what you want to discern.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like what we spoke in the talk Peripheral Awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you're thinking about death, you can't be just visualizing how you're dying, because that's not what death is for you at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a particular exemplification of that possibility, but you're not understanding the certainty of it, because certainty of death, of the possibility of death, is on the level of the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you think... Well, you could, but would it be good to think whatever situation
[SPEAKER_00]: You might have to start like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you'd get a sense of concern.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you recognize that it's that concern that needs to be developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Must not be distracted from, must not be covered up, must not be ignored.
[SPEAKER_00]: Must not be trying to get rid of it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, there's anxiety and concern.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Establishing the concern, the context of death, and then allowing it to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, through allowing it to endure, you don't need to then worry about whatever is in front of you, because it's going to be kept in check by the fundamental concern of liability to death, which is already a concern based on dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so just as a contemplation, whatever you're doing, try to see that the possibility of death there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I could, like, I'm sitting now, so how could death come up?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I could fall off my chair, hit my head,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I understand what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point I'm making is that you can do that only initially, before it becomes that mechanical just visualizations of how you might die and you lose the connection with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you can't just be focusing on what you're going to think.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to focus on that emotional background of being liable to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: In which case, you don't need to think particularly, I will die because my heart will stop while I fall off the chair.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to think, I will die, I could die, and you already feel it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's about picking up the sign.
[SPEAKER_00]: Picking up the sign, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The theme, the context, the peripheral of the actual possibilities of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is the flavor of this life?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's going to be that kind of initially unpleasant concern.
[SPEAKER_00]: Afterwards, the displeasure of that concern disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you know, it's inconceivable to be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might have apprehension and so on, but none of them would be fear and dread and pain at the prospect of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not as intoxicated with life as you were before.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you were not intoxicated because you stopped maintaining the intoxication.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that intoxication is maintained through ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: The concern about the life and that's liable to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, if you want to do meditation on death, think about like you're beating heart.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you could hear it, you could feel it beating, but can you have any intentional say?
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize no.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if this thing stops, in the same sense like a branch falls, cup gets knocked over, the heart stops.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize the heart is on the level of these random things in the world that can just change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the elements, because of the wind, because of the other... whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if that does happen, my life is over.
[SPEAKER_00]: So my life entirely, my sense of mastery, my sense of control, depends on something as silly as a cup being knocked over.
[SPEAKER_00]: A valve just... A pump, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: An electrical pump.
[SPEAKER_00]: A pump just stop... stop ceasing to pump.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or getting blocked.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just the pump gets blocked for 10 seconds, might be enough to kill me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you... that is inconceivable to have said that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, the first reaction to that is just this overwhelming concern.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, people feel fully justified.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must not think about this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once you get used to it, that concern cannot overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, literally, you have... all you have to do is just remember it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're fully back in the... back in the proper practice of that recollection of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not through, like, randomly visualizing possibilities of dying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just... my body,
[SPEAKER_00]: This is a fundamental sort of basis for my whole life, my all intentions, my past, my future, for everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, it's the basis that is fully accidental and liable to elements and I cannot even conceive having any remote input into that domain or that environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that makes you feel like... Well, that prevents you from appropriating your own life, your own intention, your own sense of control.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why if you're not overwhelmed by fear and anxiety,
[SPEAKER_00]: And you persevere through it, and you fully maintain this context, this passion is the automatic result, arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Die before you die, as Ajahn Chah said.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what about observing or contemplating death by looking at others' dying?
[SPEAKER_00]: Same.
[SPEAKER_00]: That can...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you use that to re-evoke concern for your own life and death, as a context, emotional context, that you realize
[SPEAKER_00]: I better deal with this while I can, then it's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you only use it for some sort of like a, you know, at arm's length, so to speak, not really allow it to come in because it's going to overwhelm you, and just try to, you know, observe and learn through observation, that's not death that you're learning about.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're learning about the external manifestation of someone else's death.
[SPEAKER_00]: But unless you allow it to remind you, to reconnect you with your own certain death, impending death,
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no real benefit to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly how people can be dealing with death on a daily basis and still remain fully inauthentic, full cover-up of their own death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Passionate about life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, like you can work in morgue or whatever and it might hit you initially and then you just cover it up and now it's just cadavers basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't even see that as a representation of the life that you are partaking in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It takes that... you must stop keeping it at arm's length.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you don't know how to deal with it, not keeping it at arm's length, it's going to overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's not optional for people who don't know how to deal with it, to keep it at arm's length.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the only mean of self-preservation that they know.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's going to be very frightening and scary when even that gets taken away, when they're actually dying, as that king became aware when the Buddha explained this to him.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what... that's why those people who would understand what the Buddha's teaching would freak out and they all... they will kill us.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, yeah, for any mind that hasn't been sort of restrained, that still values passion, that still values life, that still values, oh, this is mine and I am, these truths will be like frightening, terrifying, overwhelming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fall on the ground, beat their breast, pull their hair, full despair.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they realize this is inescapable.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way to escape it is to stop appropriating it internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to stop appropriating, it means you have to stop appropriating everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your likes and your dislikes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to, okay, have to see them with wisdom and fully understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that, in the beginning of that sutta that I read out,
[SPEAKER_01]: In the beginning of this talk, sir, the part I didn't read was the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll read now, because it kind of... it might make a bit more sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, go for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, the rain saturates things that are covered up.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't saturate things that are open.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, you should open up a covered thing, so the rain will not saturate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The world is beaten down by death, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't get a chance to dry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but open it up, and it won't get saturated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will get affected by the rain, as in, you're gonna get affected by death, or even by anything unpleasant, for as long as you're covering things up from yourself, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean, like, all these truths are there, obvious in a way, but you need to make the effort of undoing the cover-up for them to be discerned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like finding the new ways out.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically just stop covering up what's obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: The certainty of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: The certainty of non-control.
[SPEAKER_00]: The certainty of change.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize these things, it's through you ignoring them, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: covering them up, then you get liable and you get saturated by the rain, by the grief, by despair, by sickness, aging and death, by everything else that befalls you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It affects you because it's covered up there and it sinks into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It stays with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't go through with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through it, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these things remain the same for an arahant, but he's not affected by it, because he stopped covering these things up from him, from himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean, like, when I say self-transparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: If something's covered up, it's not transparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't see through it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, self-transparency, that we spoke about in previous talks, is developed by uncovering things up for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whenever you want to engage in sensuality or do something out of your will, wait.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remind yourself of the fundamental context of liability to death and you realize, oh, this is not worth the effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: It simply isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if I tell you, oh, look, you know, go into this place, get in.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's going to be the greatest central satisfaction of every sense you can imagine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, there's also 99% chance you're going to die.
[SPEAKER_00]: No amount of that incitement would make you enter it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're just, oh, it's not worth it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now... Or if I tell you, like, go in it, go in this place, enjoy food and whatever else, but at the end of it, within half an hour, you'll be dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must die.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't go in it, you live longer.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't go in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because suddenly, the whole enjoyment of sensual distraction and pleasure is placed in an immediate, direct, like, mirroring of the context that it's within death.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I do this, I'm dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I don't do it, I'm not dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if, say, somebody tells you like, oh, you're terminal.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have three days to live.
[SPEAKER_00]: And tomorrow, like today, you had plans for tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hanging out with your friends, some great party, careless get-drink, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, later on today, you find out that you have three days to live.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you still have interest to go around just carelessly partying with random people?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be too concerned about, is there anything I can do before I die, as in to prevent me from dying?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there anything that they can make difference to that?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize that is always the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: As soon as you're born, that's always the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: The time is too short.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can die, you will die at any given period in your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no such thing as too soon.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why we say time is too short, don't be negligent before it's too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the context of death immediately de-evaluates, takes value away from anything central.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything based on your will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, there you go.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have access to all of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, death is waiting for you at the end of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm not going to do it then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's exactly the same principle that applies to your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever you do in this life, death waits above you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you automatically become more aware.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just through discerning that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you remember the appointment.
[SPEAKER_00]: The impending appointment that can be sort of activated at any time, maybe in 50 years, maybe in 5 minutes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Also, does that make me concerned?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you be concerned about, like, I don't know, something that has no value to you, like some piece of rock, if it gets destroyed somewhere?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have no emotional connection with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you couldn't care less if you get destroyed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, if there is concern about you being destroyed, you realize, oh, so there is certain emotional connection with this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, is that emotional connection justified?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what you start uncovering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your sense of entitlement to appropriation of your own feelings, your own intentions, your own sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start uncovering it, you realize, no, this is not justified.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if these things were truly mine, if I were truly the master controller, they would not be liable to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's, that's the, again, the three divine messengers.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're telling you what's beneath it, what you'd refuse to admit to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're conveying you that message.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can only fully grasp it if you start uncovering it, start drying it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to meditate on it, set, like, set aside half an hour or whatever you have, without any distractions, think about your liability to death until you develop that context that slightly, or not so slightly, concerns you, and then just allow it to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're thinking, what do I do next?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: All I do is make sure that this context remains transparent for this half an hour that I'm meditating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if my thoughts start coming, I let them,
[SPEAKER_00]: While I still keep a quarter of an eye on that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I... if I go away and... oh, I forgot.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you go back to the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, just so to let your mind start going again, by you not losing the sight of the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the practice of mindfulness that results in samādhi that then feeds mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're learning how to not forget about the context, even when other things are happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if whatever's happening in your day-to-day life, then, you still have that context at the back of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the unshakable mindfulness, what the Buddha meant by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the proper maraṇasati.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether I'm eating, taking food, or breathing in, breathing out, the context remains at the back, and I've not lost connection with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean I must have it all the time in front of me.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means I should be able to allow it to go as far as you want, but I still won't completely lose the sight of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you think, am I... have I lost sight?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the greed a version of delusion in my mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the desire for distraction, carelessness, sensuality, ill-will, anger?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't say I'm rooted in the context anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're rooted in the context, these things cannot arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Amid sensuality, amid irritable things, they can't arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they require passion, and passion and context of death are mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Passion requires that ignoring the fact that this is all subject to this certain destruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you can't ignore that anymore, means you can't engage in passion anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what would have meant those people who are not mindful, as in those people who are not aware of that context, they're as if dead already.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're fully under that weight of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way to
[SPEAKER_00]: Not partaking it, not be affected by it, is to fully understand that context of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by being unmindful, you're fully subscribed, fully covered up, fully cocooned in that liability of certain death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means you're as if dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter if it's in five minutes or 50 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've... the life, the true meaning of life, would be that which is not
[SPEAKER_00]: permeable by death.
[SPEAKER_00]: That which is not subjected to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be the true life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or this is... this is beyond death.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you realize only understanding of death can be beyond death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything else is within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have no understanding of death, means your whole life is already as if dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: Peripheral awareness of that context will take you out of the confinements of it, through understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like you're going to develop something outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're going to just lose any passion, any appropriation, any relationship with it, with everything that's liable to death, which is five aggregates, which is your experience as a whole, your life, past, future, all of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about destroying it and not having it arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because that's... that's something you're experiencing, which means it's another thing that has a reason for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about removing the emotional connection and appropriation of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will know you're removing it, whereby if you think about losing your life, is there concern arising, is there fear, is there worry?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, I'm not holding to anything, even if death comes next second.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're practicing meditation on this, you allow it to endure for half an hour, forty minutes, an hour.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when you're not meditating,
[SPEAKER_00]: You still allow it to endure when it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it's not there as much, you try and make it back, come... bring it back, even while you have to do other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because nothing in the world is an excuse for ignoring the fact that death is certain.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's absolutely no excuse for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever you engage with, you make sure you keep the... keep... keep a corner of the eye on that fundamental context.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what you are emulating and developing in a more controlled environment, which is what meditation is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not controlled environment of mechanical method, but controlled environment of reflection and discerning the signs and tokens of how... what are the implications... how does it feel, pretty much, of being liable to death at any given moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you want to see it on that peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, okay, I'm aware of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, the mind starts thinking about things you have to do, about things that happened yesterday.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if that context is there, there will be no passion in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start losing the context, you re-establish it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's also an idea that when...
[SPEAKER_01]: I must practice, so that when death happens, I'll be able to control it in a nice way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because that's what I was describing before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for people, they're so used to just focusing what's in front of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they think, if I just learn the art of focusing,
[SPEAKER_00]: Regardless of what nature of things that I'm focusing on is, then when death comes in front of me, I'll be able to, you know, attend it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as we described in previous talks, attention is not what's in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The roots of your attention are from that peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means if you haven't addressed things on that peripheral level, by the time they're in front of you, it's too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can see that while you're still alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because truly, I mean, if you developed your focusing so far, if that were to work, focusing on the one moment in front of you, after one session, that focusing, you would be completely free from desire, from ill-will, from fear, from anything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that you're not, means no amount of focusing can help you with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only understanding that would then prevent it from affecting you in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that whole idea of I'll practice focusing so when the death comes I'll know how to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That whole idea is rooted still in that view of management.
[SPEAKER_00]: Management as in requiring to be affected and then learning how to manage it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you want to uproot it whereby it doesn't affect you in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the only way to reach the deathless in this life is to really abandon everything that is subjected to that death.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you will know that while you're still alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you wait for death to confirm it to you, means you don't know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means there won't be a confirmation you want to hear.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Arahant already knows that death that has been abandoned and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even before he dies.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before preparation, before... prepare yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to develop, if you want to practice towards not being affected by the experience of death when it comes, you start practicing towards not being affected by any experience in this life, even now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, am I affected by the arisen incitement of centrality, or ill-will, or distraction, or carelessness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I'm affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's my work.
[SPEAKER_00]: I shouldn't be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I'm not affected by that, I won't be affected by anything that comes through that... that same means of arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's death itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people think, I'll just do this focusing practice and that's somehow magically gonna result in me... controlling the death experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When death comes, I will, you know, I'll be in charge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, are you in charge now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you say no to yourself when sensuality presents itself?
[SPEAKER_00]: How many people can answer yes to that question?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I'm not even affected in the first place, let alone I have to manage my restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I'm not affected in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, here you are expecting to magically be able to deal with death, simply on account of some mechanical nostril watching practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way you won't be affected by death is if the life itself stops affecting you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you practice not being affected by life?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can only do so while you're still alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only do so by discerning what being affected is, by admitting it to yourself, by uncovering it, by understanding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you know what it is, you have a sense as well as to what you have to do in order to not be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What life is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The experiences you have in your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always a context, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always, internally, there's always a context, which is why people spend most of the time covering it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it always reveals you that which you don't want to see necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, it takes time and effort to be able to get used to seeing it and then not be suffering on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the life, saṃsara and the whole sensuality goes with the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's effortless to turn a blind eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's effortless to engage with centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to start making the effort to pull yourself out of it before you'll be able to appreciate then the restraint, solitude, non-distraction, non-ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't naturally value those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Effort and wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the meditation practice, allowing that context, concerning context of death to endure, means allowing a degree of fear to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: And not, don't, don't give in to trying to get rid of it, right away.
[SPEAKER_00]: But allow it to be there, while then the mind is thinking other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't automatically
[SPEAKER_00]: Fear, unpleasant, I must get rid of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever I do, I must get rid of this anxiety on account of context of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't affect you do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're the one who chooses to do things on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize I can choose not to do anything on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can just allow it to be there for as long as he wants to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you automatically strengthen your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you automatically uncover anything you've been covering up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, it's gonna take time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you invest a lot of time in covering it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the context of death is enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're seated, in your room, in your kuti, whatever, a layperson, a monk, not distracted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't even have to watch it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Watch it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just don't rush into overly defining it necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's gonna become rooted in trying to get rid of that unpleasant aspect of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just allow it to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And sometimes that endurance will be clearer, as in it's going to be more present, sometimes it will be less.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you still recognize it to a degree it's still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then you... if there is nothing else going on, because it shouldn't be, you're in that protected meditation environment, no distractions, as I said, let it endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you have a thought of
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, after this, I must do this, this, this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, now, you look at, you see that thought against that backdrop of the context of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, things that you must do, your duties, are now seen against the context of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you have a memory of something that happened in the past that bothers you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, against the context of death, that memory has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already, you're not as bothered as much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you got a bigger picture now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not sucked into what bothers you, because you stopped trying to get rid of the unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now you have the ultimate unpleasant, the prospect of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any other more inferior unpleasant won't be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if those thoughts present themselves, you let them present themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't try to overanalyze it, overthink it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just make sure, don't forget about a context of that certain death that I'm concerned about right now in my meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: While I let my mind think what it wants to think.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the point will come, if you keep doing it, whereby the context will be immovable, imperturbable, in regard to whatever your mind thinks.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will recognize also that the only way to perturb it, is to intentionally choose to do so, by saying yes to sensuality carelessly, saying yes to ill-will carelessly, saying yes to distraction carelessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'll think about that later.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a careless choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not thinking about that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point I'm making.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not, I'm thinking about it, I'm dead, I'm gonna be dead, I'm gonna be dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there, enduring on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're actually thinking about your duties, or things that bother you, or things that you like.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you're thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, on the basis of the context that you discerned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that context is there, peripherally, as a container of all these things that you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means there will be less and less ground.
[SPEAKER_00]: The longer that context endures, less and less basis for passion towards these particular things will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is effortless as well, because you're not thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is abstain from intentionally covering it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And abstaining is effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't require you to do something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just requires you to not do something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's what meditation is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever your object.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's to say, it establishes his mind in the divine abiding of the jhāna, and whether he sits, walks, urinates, defecates, eats, his mind is divine in that state.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all these things are inferior to his establishment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Establish your mind in the context of death, certain death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely no... not even a grain of opportunity for passion to arise, if that context fully saturates your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the context is on the... there, on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what things are generally subjected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a factual context.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason it's not saturating anything is because you're covering it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You covered it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you keep maintaining that covering up through engaging with unwholesome centrality of will and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't create this?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, you don't create the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the Buddha said it's just an ancient path that was covered.
[SPEAKER_00]: He uncovered it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't create anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just discernment of these factual universal truths.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what meditation should be revolving around.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter if you do it for 15 minutes or for 5 hours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Establish your mind upon the greater context that... that is infertile basis for any passion, any ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: They cannot exist on that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you let the context endure until your mind gets established in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you know your mind is established in it when you cannot be passionate.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot be affected by the arisen feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant, unpleasant or neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you also know when you're about to do something, if it's gonna make you firmly, more firmly established in that context, or it's gonna take you away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The choice becomes much clearer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is unwholesome, this is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unwholesome means takes you away from the wholesome context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wholesome means keeps you within a wholesome context.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the basis within that domain, doesn't contradict it, doesn't abolish it, doesn't drag you down from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why like Devadatta in the suttas, once he started engaging in unwholesome acts, he was unable to establish his mind in jhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wasn't some magical energy that got trapped or evaporated.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just unwholesome, contradicts the domain of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you choose to engage in it, you choose to then forsake this, the greater context.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only way to develop greater context is to keep discerning it, keep thinking about it, keep trying to establish it, allowing it to endure, not trying to get rid of it if it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you can't crave for it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't crave for jhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't crave for the imperturbable, wholesome samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because craving is always towards the actual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling in regard to the actual thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you crave for.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this is the context of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now your mind is establishing that, which means your mind then became unreachable by any craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, no room for anything that's based on that craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality, ill-will, delusion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if people wonder, how do I make this context endure?
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't, oh, it's enduring, I'm making it endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's like you still trying to make it actual in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you make it endure, but stop trying to make it endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You make it endure by thinking about it,
[SPEAKER_00]: But by not interfering about it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the same sense, how do you... like, as we gave the example of the appointment, life-changing appointment you have, you don't need to make it endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is stop distracting yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't cancel that appointment.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can't cancel this appointment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, okay, the recognition of that, it's already a form of endurance, even if I don't necessarily feel fully concerned about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Still, I am aware the context of whatever I do, it's gonna end.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of it is subjected.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can end even before I... before I realize it will end.
[SPEAKER_00]: My beating heart right now can stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Have that... allow that thought to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't overthink it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't give in to fear of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just allow it to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Allow that thought to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then see other things that appear in your mind against enduring of that thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not looking for a specific answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is what it is, or this is how it will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're looking for the, like, evoking of the context of being liable to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you create that connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, while I'm sitting here, breathing, secluded from unwholesome, secluded from distraction, what if this beating muscle in my chest were to stop?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't answer it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't provide an excuse or an explanation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just allow that question to sink in.
[SPEAKER_00]: What if it were to stop?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then mind, well, this, this, this, all that is secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Still, allow just the question to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then the thought comes, it will stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Allow that to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, your timer rings, your meditation finished.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you realize that context still hasn't changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, okay, you go and do your duty now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you still have that context enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you will forget it only when you engage in unwholesome, lust, aversion or delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, yes, you need to meditate in this manner as much as you can, until that context becomes imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you could also see you need, like, a basis of sense restraint, physical restraint, as a... as a... as a guardian, whereby your context is lost, but your bodily behavior, speech behavior, even your mental behavior, doesn't take you as far back into the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you won't have to undo it as much.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the virtue comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the context is enduring now, you still haven't forgotten that your beating heart might stop, that you're fundamentally liable to death, you have a degree of concern.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do I do now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you include the thought of what do I do now against that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize you don't do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the context still there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever were to happen to me, would it be against the backdrop of that context?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever I were to do with my life, choose immediately or for the future, is this context changeable?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, are my engagements with life or with people, are they worthy?
[SPEAKER_00]: Against this context, in this new light of the new context, is it worthy being like, you know, doing this or doing that, or being so emotionally disturbed and kind of not getting what I want?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't even then...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're in that context, being affected by things such as sensuality and so on, if you're truly in that context, being affected by those things becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even at that very time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure, you can forget about the context and then be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you're in the context, it is truly imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you need to do is find ways of maintaining the context, regardless whether you're sitting in a protected meditation environment or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, seated, walking, lying down, extending his arms, eating, urinating, defecating, whatever you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You maintain the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Day and night.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the extent necessary for obliterating all, any ground for any passion to manifest again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Passion, not things that you're passionate towards.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, that's the meditation object of death.